Now that you know all about Python, you know how to set up your environment, I'm going to
quickly show you the anatomy of a Python program. Note that you don't need to understand
everything that's happening in the program, so don't worry, don't panic. You're going to understand
all of the concepts throughout the course of the day, but I want to show you what some typical
Python code might look like and what it does and break it down into pieces. So here I have a
Python program for using the GitHub search API and I'm going to open this up in my editor so
that I can walk through it and I'm going to run it and we'll see some results.
So first line, I'm importing requests. This is a package import. In this case,
requests is a third party package that I would need to install in my virtual environment before
running this program since it's not included in Python standard library. Then I'm going ahead and
defining a GitHub API URL. So what this piece of code is going to do is it's going to use the
public GitHub search API and it's going to pass in a query asking for repositories and
particular languages that have more than a set number of stars. These are methods and you can tell
because they have the deaf keyword in front of them and some code that is indented to the right
of them. But for the time being, I'm going to scroll all the way down and this code is only 40 lines.
So once you start getting more familiar in Python, you'll have no trouble reading this line
by line and understanding exactly what it does. But the thing that I'm scrolling down to is on
930 and it says if underscore underscore name underscore underscore is equal to underscore main
in quotes that's a string. This is how Python knows whether the main method is being run. So
when we start a Python program from the command line, this is going to be the point of entry.
Here I'm defining a list and this is a list of what languages I would like to query for. In this
case, it's Python, JavaScript, and Ruby. And then I'm calling a method that is defined in this file
called ripos with most stars. And I'm passing in the list of languages as an argument.
Now, in VS code, I can in Mac command click or in Windows control click onto this method and it
will automatically jump and bring me straight to it in the code. This method is defined in line 16.
So first, I am creating a query with that list of languages. Create query is another method that
I've defined in this file. Let's jump up to that. This one takes a list of languages and a second
argument. Here, I'm providing a default value of 60,000 as the second argument. So if that second
argument is not provided, it's going to use the default. Then I'm going to build up my query.
This is something called an F string and Python or a string with built-in formatting.
And this allows me to provide a variable inside of curly braces. Just like this. And the
representation of that variable is going to get inserted right into the string. So I start building
my base query and then I loop through every language in the list of languages and I append
onto my query, a string that looks like this. So a sample query that might be generated from this
method looks like this comment right here. Stars, colon greater than 50, language, colon Python,
a space language, colon JavaScript. This is syntax that the GitHub search API expects as part of
a query. And then it returns the built-up query. Now we're back in the repos with most
stars method. I'm going to build a dictionary that's defined with these curly braces.
The first entry in this dictionary has a key of Q and a value of query, a key of sort
that is going to be in this case the default value, which is sort by the number of stars.
And then also a key of order. It will have the value of desk for descending.
I'm going to get a response from the GitHub API by using this request library. The request
library provides a .get method that maps to HTTP get, where I pass in the URL and then that
dictionary of parameters that I built online a team. And then I'm going to get the status code
in the response. So for those of you familiar with APIs, it might be 200 for okay for for
not found. Maybe 503 if I was an authorized, doesn't matter to me. If I got back a status code
that was not 200. Oh, sorry. I have Liga Church turned on for myself. I will turn those off for
all of you at the next break because what this should actually look like is not equals without
a space in between. I just have a fancy setup. So for that I apologize. But I'm checking here that
if the status code does not equal 200, I'm going to raise the runtime error. My program just
going to quit. I got an error code. I don't know what it is. I don't know where to go from here.
Otherwise, I'm going to get the JSON from the response. Save it in a variable called response
underscore JSON. And then I'm going to return the items key in that response JSON back to the
calling main method. So now I'm here. I've gotten the results from the repos with most stars
method right up here. And now I'm going to loop through every result in that list of results.
And I'm going to get the language, which I know from reading the hub API docs that it's going to be
in a JSON format that's going to have a language key, a star geysers count key, which is the number
of people who have started that repository. And it's also going to have the name of the repository.
Then for every result in these results, I'm going to use one of these F strings to print out an
arrow. The name of the repo is a language repo with these many stars. So it's pretty short
program. It's only 40 lines of code. I like to think that this is pretty readable. Do you folks think
that this is readable? Yeah, it's compact and condensed. It's pretty straightforward. What's happening.
And let's go ahead and run this. And I'm just going to do that by opening up the command palette
and then selecting run Python file and terminal. I think I already, this is something that you might
run into. If you already have a REPL open in your terminal and you select run Python file
in terminal, VS code is going to try to paste in the commands to run the file into your REPL
and then REPL is going to explode. So if you see something like this, you know, this is the fully
qualified path to the Python executable on my system. And the file that I'm trying to run,
if you see that and like invalid syntax, know that you just need to exit out of your REPL or
open a new terminal here with plus before you try running that again. So let's try that again.
I'm going to select Python run file in terminal and now it works successfully. And this went and
reached out to the GitHub API and pretty quickly returned this list of some of the top Python
JavaScript and I forget the third language. What was the third one? Let's see Ruby. I guess there
are no Ruby repositories with over 60,000 stars. The GitHub search API, it doesn't always return
super accurate values just in FYI. It optimizes for returning quickly versus super accurate results.
So if you run this multiple times, you might get multiple different results.
But that was it. It was pretty straightforward. It used a lot of the language features that we
are going to learn today. And it's a really quick and easy way to interact with APIs,
interact with data and automate a lot of the tasks that you might have to do day-to-day.